All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is נ"ח, Nunchas,
58. And we pick up at the bottom of נ"ז עמוד ב',
Nun-zayin amud bais, the first wide line, הגיע זמן ולא נישאו. higia
zman velo nisu. We have now been introduced to the idea that
when either the husband or sometimes interestingly the wife says that it's
time to move from קידושין kiddushin to נישואין, nisuin, the other side
has a right to be asked for to be given twelve months.
Not exactly clear what happens if they refuse, if let's say she
refuses. If he refuses, then he has to start paying the bills.
But if she refuses, it's not exactly clear. תוספות Tosafos discusses certain
penalties would be fined. Anyway, they have a right to postpone for
twelve months to get everything in order. And what we learned was
that for a קטנה, katana, the rabbis both you know encouraged or
let's say they discouraged doing the נישואין nisuin while she was a
קטנה. katana. They say she and the father can postpone the entire
period of her being a קטנה. katana. That's important because we talk
about קידושי קטנה, kiddushei katana, but the actual living together was not
supposed to begin until at least she was a נערה, naara, twelve
and a half. And we learned that by a בוגרת, bogeres, you
don't even have to wait for one of them to demand it,
or excuse me,
that as soon as she becomes a בוגרת, bogeres, the clock starts
ticking automatically. So the whole idea of demanding and twelve months would
happen during the period of נערה. naara. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues on the first wide line, הגיע
זמן ולא נישאו, higia zman velo nisu, exactly this point, that when
the time has arrived, then he has to start paying the bills
and he can actually provide her תרומה Terumah food. And the question
is how much תרומה, Terumah, how much חולין? Chulin? And thank you,
and the גמרא, Gemara, the very first דף daf of the גמרא
Gemara discussed what's the reason for the delay: his fault or her
fault or nobody's fault? That's not the discussion here. הגיע זמן ולא
נישאו. higia zman velo nisu. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, so now we're
going to deal with the fact about why she's allowed to eat
תרומה Terumah after twelve months
because you know she's married to a כהן kohen but it's only
קידושין kiddushin not נישואין. nisuin. So she's eating תרומה Terumah after twelve
months if that's how he's feeding her, you know paying for giving
providing her תרומה, Terumah, then presumably biblically she's allowed to do this.
אמר עולא דבר תורה ארוסה בת ישראל אוכלת בתרומה. Amar Ulla devar
Torah arusah bas Yisrael ocheles biterumah. So we have to assume that
even just at the stage of אירוסין, erusin, in principle she's allowed
to eat תרומה Terumah because that's what happens after twelve months even
though it's not yet נישואין. nisuin. שנאמר וכהן כי יקנה נפש קנין
כספו. Shene'emar v'kohen ki yikneh nefesh kinyan kaspo. When a כהן kohen
purchases a soul, the purchase of his money, you know a money
purchase, and the simple sense of the verse is talking about purchasing
a slave who eats תרומה. Terumah. But the גמרא Gemara says והאי
נמי קנין כספו הוא. vehai nami kinyan kaspo hu. So and a
wife is the purchase of his money. The first דף daf in
קידושין, kiddushin, right, is that a אשה isha is נקנית niknes through
money. And that's obviously something that we will discuss when we do
מסכת קידושין. Maseches Kiddushin. How much is this seen as like classic
acquisition and ownership or not? But at least for now without getting
into that, we can acknowledge that the קידושין kiddushin occurs through a
transfer of money and therefore it is in the category of קנין
כספו kinyan kaspo and therefore the wife, and that is sometimes the
important point is that is the act of קידושין. kiddushin. And therefore
she can eat from קידושין. kiddushin. Okay. Now the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, I
should say, does not learn it out from קנין כספו, kinyan kaspo,
learns it out from ביתו. beiso. When it says that the house
of the כהן kohen eats תרומה, Terumah, ביתו זו אשתו. beiso zo
ishto. Now בית bayis normally suggests the period of נישואין. nisuin. So
it seems that there actually is a debate of the בבלי Bavli
and ירושלמי Yerushalmi whether in principle you have to wait till נישואין
nisuin or not. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi that's if you say that you
really biblically need to wait till נישואין, nisuin, then you would have
to argue that once the twelve months arrive, since there's an obligation
to get married and since he is paying for her food bills,
that is enough considered close enough to נישואין nisuin that it would
constitute this idea of being ביתו, beiso, his household. But the בבלי
Bavli does not say that. The בבלי Bavli says in principle even
straight from the moment of אירוסין, erusin, קנין כספו kinyan kaspo she
can eat תרומה. Terumah. And that's why once the twelve months have
arrived, she we begin to allow it because really in principle she
could have eaten תרומה Terumah from day one after the קידושין. kiddushin.
Yes.
Does the בבלי Bavli understand that the legal force of קנין כספו
kinyan kaspo has to do kicks in his obligations or her rights
or both?
No, her rights. This is all about her right to eat תרומה.
Terumah. In the תורה, Torah, we're not talking at all about his
obligation to pay for the food bills. That might be rabbinic anyway.
So we're just talking about her right to eat תרומה. Terumah. Right,
that תרומה Terumah it's not considered like a זר, zar, a non-כהן
kohen who's eating תרומה. Terumah. She's part of the כהן's kohen household.
Didn't we talk about קידושין kiddushin a few days ago where we
said she didn't eat תרומה Terumah until she until twelve months?
No, she doesn't eat תרומה Terumah until נישואין nisuin or if she's
been until twelve months when he's supposed to have the נישואין. nisuin.
But we're saying but since she's not yet נישואין nisuin at twelve
months, we have to establish that biblically she's entitled already from קידושין,
kiddushin, or else how could you allow her to eat after twelve
months? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara now says, so now we're going
to deal with so why do we not allow it if biblically
it is allowed from the time of קידושין? kiddushin? So the גמרא
Gemara says ומה טעם אמרו אינה אוכלת. u'mah ta'am amru einah ocheles.
So why did they say that after קידושין kiddushin the wife of
a כהן... kohen... should not eat תרומה, terumah, again, this is not
about who pays the food bills, but should not eat תרומה, terumah,
שמא ימזגו לה כוס בבית אביה, shema yimze'gu lah kos b'veit aviha,
because they'll pour her a cup of wine. See, when you normally
think of תרומה, terumah, I'm thinking of grain, but obviously a major
area of תרומה terumah is from the grapes and from the wine.
So they'll pour her, they'll pour her a cup of wine in
her father's house and say, you know, and here, here's some of
your תרומה. terumah. Now presumably, ותשקהו לאחיה ולאחותה, v'tashkehu l'achia ul'achota, and
she'll go and have her brother, her brother and sister drink. Okay,
so basically while she's living in her father's house, it's a dangerous
thing for her to be eating תרומה. terumah. So even though technically
she's allowed, the rabbis forbade it, but they allowed it after twelve
months once he had to start paying the food bills. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי, ee hachi, if that's true, הגיע זמן
ולא נישאו נמי, higia zman v'lo nisu nami, so even when the
time comes to get married and he has to start paying the
food bills, it might be you're going easy on him by letting
him pay it with תרומה, terumah, but why shouldn't we be concerned
that she'll share it with members of her household? So the גמרא
Gemara says no, התם דוכתא מייחד לה, hatam duchtam m'yached lah,
once the time has come, the twelve months to get married, even
if they're not yet, the wedding's been postponed for some reason, he
like designates a special house for her, a special place for her.
You want her out of the father's house, which is interesting. It
puts her in this like limbo stage, right? So for that time
of קידושין, kiddushin, she's fully in the father's house. נישואין, nissuin, she's
fully in the groom to in you know in her new husband's
house. We discussed the whole idea of giving her over to the
שליחים, shluchim, leaving the father's house, not yet arriving at the groom's
house, that was a certain type of a limbo stage. Here we
just talk about a type of a social reality that once the
twelve months arrive, he will want to have her, you know, live
apart from her father, he'll set her up in an apartment for
the next few months until the wedding can take place, which is
interesting.
Yeah, which is interesting. I mean, let's say the groom does not
have so much money to pay for a third place. Yeah, it's
very funny that the גמרא Gemara assumes that that's like a such
a wide reality that we can rely on that. Okay, anyway, the
גמרא Gemara says, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, if this is true, that
we're so concerned that people will like share and therefore we can't
give them the תרומה terumah that they might be allowed to eat,
if that's true, is that me? I'm sorry, that's me. אי הכי,
ee hachi, if that's true, לקיט כהן לישראל, lakit kohen l'yisrael,
if a כהן kohen is a like a worker for a Jew,
for a non-כהן, kohen, and he לא יאכל בתרומה, lo yochal b'truma,
he shouldn't be allowed to eat תרומה terumah like he brings his
bag lunch, takes out his תרומה terumah sandwich, we shouldn't allow that.
Why? דילמא אתי למיכל בהדיה, dilma ati l'meichal bahadei, maybe he'll have
his boss, he'll share his sandwich with his boss. So the גמרא
Gemara says one minute. I mean, that's a little, that's a huge
difference, right? There you're just temporarily working in your boss's yard as
opposed to living with your family. It's a little bit of a
difference. So the גמרא Gemara says, השתא מדידיה ספו ליה, hasha mididei
safu leh,
one minute, there they anyway they feed him, it's on their bill.
So maybe it's not even him bringing his sandwich from home, maybe
the boss is giving him תרומה, terumah, the boss anyway is providing
some food for his workers.
Right, exactly.
Like you got exactly, you got vegetarian, vegan, and כהן, kohen, right.
Okay.
מדידיה אכיל,
mididei
achil,
he's going to actually ask to eat from the כהן kohen sandwich?
It's not the same reality, we're not concerned about it. Okay. רב
שמואל בר רב יהודה אמר משום סימפון. Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yehuda
amar mishum simpon. So that's one reason, which is a very reasonable
reason. We don't want her eating while she's still living in her
father's house because she'll come to share with her family. Now, רב
שמואל בר רב יהודה אמר משום סימפון. Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yehuda
amar mishum simpon. No,
we're afraid of סימפון, simpon, again this must be some Greek word
or something, but it means some type of a defect that is
going to cause the wedding to be called off or to be
reversed, I should say. So סימפון simpon is like, you know, again
this is a phrase used from like מקח וממכר mekach umemkar from
like the standard area of purchase going back to the קנין כספו
kinyan kaspo model. You go ahead and you buy a car and
then you find out that the radiator is missing or something. You
know, so that's like okay, the whole thing was a מקח טעות,
mekach ta'ut, it was a major flaw, a major defect. So here,
what's going to happen when they actually start living together, he has
sex with her, you know, and they're intimate and then he realizes
something about her that he didn't realize before and then it'll be
a מקח טעות mekach ta'ut and everything will be null and void
and she won't have been married even from the time of קידושין
kiddushin because he'll realize that there was something that I wasn't aware
of that therefore the whole thing is null and void and therefore
all the eating, it could in theory work the other way around,
we'll get to it, by קידושין kiddushin it is possible that there's
a מקח טעות mekach ta'ut in the reverse. A common example as
I've said today that פוסקים poskim deal with is turns out that
the guy was gay.
So, anyway, in those cases the whole thing will be and that's
something you find out after you've been intimate.
Anyway, in those cases she'll have been eating תרומה terumah from the
time
of
קידושין kiddushin unjustifiably. Yes, Charlie.
Wouldn't she need a גט get under such circumstances?
No, if it's a קידושי טעות, kidushi taus, it means it was
never binding at the outset. And so, you know, that's why sometimes
it's really important, like in these cases, to identify a קידושי טעות
kidushi taus if the husband is refusing to give a גט. get.
And there definitely have been more than one cases, as I said,
with the guy turning out to be gay, where that's been an
issue. Yes.
Can a כהן kohen eat non-תרומה? trumah?
What? Can a כהן? kohen?
Yes, certainly. Yes, certainly. Yeah, so it wouldn't be a problem in
either case. So okay. So now the problem is going to be,
okay, we get that reason, but then the question is like, you
know, how does the twelve months solve the problem which the גמרא
Gemara will get to a little bit later today? Because if it's
after twelve months, that should still be a concern. But the גמרא
Gemara even pushes it beyond the twelve months. How is it okay
once there's חופה? chupah? We say she can eat the תרומה trumah
once there's חופה. chupah. They haven't been completely intimate yet at that
stage. So says the גמרא, Gemara, אי הכי ניכנסה לחופה ולא ניבעלה?
ee hachi nichnesah l'chupah v'lo nivalah? So once you have the חופה
chupah before there's been sex, נמי, nami, should still be a problem.
We shouldn't allow it until after sex. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, התם מיבדק בדיק לה והדר מינסב. hasam mivdak badik lah v'hadar
minasav. There,
before he actually goes ahead and spends the twenty thousand dollars, maybe
it's fifty thousand dollars at this stage, then he's going to spend
time getting to spend more time talking to her, getting to know
her better. So maybe they won't have been to the stage of
being physically intimate, but at least once it's actually the time of
the wedding itself,
we feel confident enough that there's not going to be a
ביטול קידושין.
bitul kidushin. Okay? I thought there's a whole thing when they're intimate.
That is a possibility. You have to understand, the first stage of
the קידושין, kidushin, they haven't been dating. The first stage of the
קידושין kidushin might have been some arrangement with the father when she
was five years old. So he really doesn't know her at all.
Before we're actually going to go ahead and have the whole חופה
chupah and the wedding and send out the invitations and spend all
that money, they're actually going to get to spend some time together
getting to know one another. It doesn't mean that they're actually going
to be physically intimate. So after that stage, we feel confident enough
it's not going to be a ביטול קידושין, bitul kidushin, even though,
yes, there is a small chance that after they're intimate, there will
be a problem.
That sounds like a גזירה gezeirah wouldn't be had about that, it
was always חייש...
chaysh... Yeah, that's true. Anyway, but that is correct, meaning the גמרא
Gemara concedes that it's not, you know, that we haven't eliminated all
concerns, but at least it's significantly different than from the time of
קידושין.
kidushin. Our concern for providing for the woman outweighs our concern of
ביטול קידושין. bitul kidushin.
Exactly. Although what twelve months does is not clear and the גמרא
Gemara will get to that. It's one thing you wait till the
day of the wedding, okay, but obviously that could be a sliding
scale, so we'll get to that in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara asks a similar question.
אלא מעתה עבד כהן שלקחו מישראל לא יאכל בתרומה משום סימפון? ella
me'ata eved kohen she'lakacho mi'Yisrael lo yochal b'trumah mishum simpon? So similar
to the previous question except in reverse. A כהן kohen buys a
ישראל Yisrael slave. And that's, right, a slave of a כהן kohen
eats תרומה. trumah. He shouldn't eat תרומה trumah because maybe they'll find
some problem with the slave, right? And therefore that'll be a מקח
טעות. mekach taus. I didn't realize that the slave was lame. I
didn't realize that he had a medical condition or whatever. And it's
a מקח טעות mekach taus and then the slave will be eating
תרומה trumah unjustifiably. So the גמרא Gemara says no, סימפון בעבדים ליכא.
simpon b'avadim leika. We're not concerned about some flaw with the slave.
Why not? דאי דעילאי הא קחזי ליה. de'ee d'eilai ha kachazi leh.
If it's something that's visible externally,
then you could see it. So something like I don't know, like
you know, a broken arm, you know, a limp or whatever, things
that would affect his work that you could visibly see. So you'll
see. And if you didn't see, that's your fault. You can't claim
that it was a טעות, taus, a mistake. ואי דגואי, v'ee d'gavai,
if it's something more private, internal, so
which presumably means like private, something you would see when his clothes
were off, so למלאכה קבעי. l'mlacha kaba'ei.
So you need him for work. What do you care about what
he looks like naked or things of that nature? That's not relevant.
Okay, of course, the problem is like I said, what about if
he's got some illness that's, you know, some type of a thing?
So anyway, the גמרא Gemara says ושבסתר לא איכפת ליה? v'she'ba'seser lo
ichpas leh?
So are you telling me that things that are not visible are
not of your concern? Here's some example of things that are not
visible. How
about
נמצא גנב, nimtza ganav, let's say it turns out that he's a
thief, או קוביוסטוס, o kuvyustus, or a קוביוסטוס? kuvyustus? Which רש"י Rashi
says means that he's a what do you call that, he's a
that he's a kidnapper. תוספות Tosafot says that קוביוסטוס kuvyustus is not
a kidnapper. תוספות Tosafot says it means he's like a dice player,
okay? I don't know why, I'm sorry, קובייא, kubya, yeah. I'm sorry,
what does Steinsaltz say there? Does he... I'm sure it's a Greek
word.
It is, yeah. Kidnapper. ArtScroll's
going
by רש"י.
Rashi. Okay. Anyway, or you find out he's a gambler or a
kidnapper, related professions I guess. Anyway, הכי
הוא? hachi hu? So that's... So, that's your fault. You got what's
coming to you. Now what does that mean?
So, the point is that
the way רש"י Rashi says is, you should have expected that. Slaves,
often slaves are card play—I mean, this just obviously speaks about society's
attitude when there were slaves, they assigned a lot of
attributes to the slaves. So, they say, "Okay, that was to be
expected that he might be a thief or card player. You can't,
you can't say that it's a ביטול מקח." Bitul Mekach. מאי איכא?
Mai ika? So, what's the only thing that maybe you could say
you didn't expect and it turned out? לסטים מזויין, Listim Mezuyan, if
he turns out to be like an armed bandit. Not just a
סתם stam petty thief.
Not just a kidnapper.
Exactly. Well, for רש"י, Rashi, the kidnapper is pretty funny, but let's
go with תוספות. Tosafot. Not like a סתם stam petty thief or
card player. But he turns out to be like a real armed
robber. או מוכתב למלכות, O muchtav lamalchut, or that maybe he was
already designated for execution by the government. Other things that are not
visible that are real problems. Or a felon. An escaped felon.
הנהו קלא אית להו. Hanehu kala it lehu. Those are public. Those
are things that would be well known. And therefore, if you didn't
bother to find out about it, you got what's coming to you.
It's sort of like buyer beware. The seller is not—if this is
like a matter of public information, you cannot claim מקח טעות. Mekach
taut. So,
רש"י Rashi says it means you knew it and you were okay
with it. תוספות Tosafot says more reasonably, even if you didn't know
it, you cannot claim מקח טעות. Mekach taut. Things that you were
able to find out and were relatively well known, it's your responsibility
to find out.
If you didn't and therefore you're suffering because
we assume for your stupidity.
You're not punished.
It's a question about whose responsibility is it. You cannot claim that
you were duped into this sale. When you enter into a sale,
it's your responsibility to clarify the issues
that are of public record and knowable. And if not, then you're
implicitly accepting whatever you get. It's sort of like the phrase of
כי הא. Ki ha. You're implicitly accepting what you get. You know
the rules of the game. You know you're supposed to check into
it.
If you
didn't and you don't say anything, you say, "No, no problems whatsoever."
Oh, if I lied to you and you asked me, that might
be different.
So, the גמרא Gemara says, "Alright."
So, anyway, now of course, as I say, we can imagine other
things that are not obvious and that you didn't have a way
of knowing. But anyway, that's the גמרא's Gemara basic answer. So, the
concern is, one is a concern that the קידושין Kiddushin will be
בטל batel and she'll be eating תרומה terumah improperly retroactively. The other
is a concern that she'll be sharing with her family. And therefore
we said don't do it. Don't do it from קידושין, Kiddushin, only
do it from נישואין. Nissu'in. But we allowed it after twelve months.
So, the גמרא Gemara says, מאי בינייהו? Mai beinaihu? איכא בינייהו Ika
beinaihu קבל ומסר והלך. kabal u-masar ve-halach.
So, what would be a difference, a case that maybe these concerns
would not be present? So, one would be קבל, kabal, קיבל. kibel.
The husband said, "Whatever turns out to be about you that I
don't know at this stage, I'm okay with.
I accept however things turn out. I'm not going to do any
ביטול מקח." bitul mekach. So, in that case, maybe she'd be allowed
to start eating from the time of קידושין Kiddushin according to one
approach. According to the approach that she'll share with her family, she
would not. Or מסר והלך, masar ve-halach,
the case we had earlier when the father sends her out of
the father's house to go to the חתן chatan with the messengers,
and she's being brought to the חתן's chatan house. So, she's out
of the father's house, but she's not yet in the חתן's chatan
house. She's in that limbo state. Everybody remember that before? That stage?
So, that's a stage where she's out of the father's house. So,
maybe she can eat תרומה terumah at that stage, because she's not
going to share with her father. On the other hand, there might
be still a ביטול מקח bitul mekach concern, and therefore from the
other approach she should not eat. It's interesting. מסר והלך masar ve-halach
is one idea.
But that's not like living in an apartment until the time. That's
like a three-day journey to get to the city.
Exactly, exactly. Now, it is an interesting question. How about—what if the
גמרא Gemara said, "What about a case about a בוגרת, bogeret, a
woman who's twenty, who's living alone and so on?" What's also funny
is that the גמרא Gemara assumes that we would make case-by-case exceptions
of this. Normally we sort of adopt a לא פלוג lo plug
type of approach. It's one thing to say that they should be
getting married, it's the twelve months, and so on. That's a
very defined category. To start doing case-by-case analysis differences is unusual.
But you have to, right? If it's compared to מקח טעות mekach
taut in business, you also have to distinguish.
No, that you have to distinguish whether it was a מקח טעות,
mekach taut, but whether we allow her to eat תרומה, terumah, we
could make a לא פלוג. lo plug. Alright. So, now we figure
out how much—so now we know that after twelve months she's allowed
to eat תרומה. terumah. We're still going to figure out exactly why
if it's a concern of מקח טעות, mekach taut, but we've already
sort of seen the general approach. And now we're going to figure
out how much is he allowed to give her תרומה terumah because
she has to be more careful with it in general and she
has to— can't eat it while she's a נדה. niddah. At the
time of the משנה Mishnah it should be noted that a woman
was a נדה niddah only one week out of the month, right,
from the time the bleeding
began for a week. The whole idea of waiting seven days of
non-bleeding
began later
in the time of the גמרא, Gemara, and that led to a
woman being a נדה niddah about one-third of the month. But now
it's real but at the time of the משנה Mishnah it's really
only a quarter of the month. So it's interesting that you have
an opinion that says he can give the whole thing תרומה. terumah.
What does she do during that one week? There's another opinion that
says half תרומה terumah and half חולין. chulin. You don't really need
half חולין chulin because he only needs חולין chulin for the one
week out of the month, so you only need a quarter חולין.
chulin. But again, it's harder to handle תרומה, terumah, so you have
these types of these different opinions. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. רבי טרפון אומר נותן לה הכל תרומה. Rabbi Tarfon omer
noten la kol terumah. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, מחלוקת, machlokes,
and here again we're going to make distinctions, although this already makes
a lot more sense. מחלוקת בבת כהן לכהן. Machlokes be-vas kohen le-kohen.
When is the debate about whether you can give her all תרומה
terumah or half and half? If it's a daughter of a כהן
kohen married to a כהן. kohen. So therefore it's a woman who
already knows—remember, she hasn't yet started living with her husband the כהן.
kohen. She's still living, she's still in her father's house or she's
wherever she is, she hasn't yet started living. So if she's a
בת ישראל, bas Yisrael, she's never started—she's never handled תרומה terumah in
her life. She doesn't know about how to be careful. She doesn't
know what the rules are. We're going to start giving her תרומה?
terumah? How's she going to know what to do? So therefore he
says the only possibility that we would give her full תרומה, terumah,
all תרומה, terumah, is if she was a בת כהן. bas kohen.
She already knew about תרומה terumah and about the rules. So therefore
she could be careful even during the period when she's טמא. tamei.
אבל בבת ישראל לכהן, Aval be-vas Yisrael le-kohen, if it's a normal
ישראל Yisrael woman marrying a כהן, kohen, דברי הכל מחצה חולין מחצה
תרומה. divrei hakol mechtza chulin mechtza terumah. So then everybody would agree
half and half. I mean, we would still assume that she could
be careful enough for half the month, but we would still want
to give her, not make it too much of a burden, certainly
when she's a נדה. niddah. And just in general, make it a
more manageable in terms of handling the food. So it's an interesting
middle place, that we assume she knows enough to be able to
handle a reasonable demand but not an unreasonable demand. Also there might
be a little bit too much of a יצר הרע. yetzer hara.
If we give her all תרומה, terumah, she has to sell it
and buy חולין chulin instead. So for a בת כהן, bas kohen,
we trust that she'll be careful enough to do that. So for
a בת ישראל bas Yisrael who's never used to תרומה terumah and
maybe doesn't appreciate the weightiness of it or all of the laws
etc., we don't want to be sort of like putting a מכשול
michshol in front of her and giving her תרומה terumah at a
time when she needs to eat חולין.
chulin. Wouldn't he be expected to do what's normal, like to do
for a woman? I mean, he's married to her, right? Yeah. And
when she was actually נדה, niddah, he couldn't give her תרומה. terumah.
Right. I mean, he would presumably be giving her חולין. chulin. So
it doesn't make sense.
Yeah, it's very bizarre. I really don't understand the idea. On the
other hand, she's—he's not yet married and his real obligations haven't begun
yet. But I mean, to me it seems that it's just going
a little bit easy on the בעל baal in this case. But
yeah, it doesn't make any sense that he should be entitled to
give her תרומה terumah at the period when she's a נדה, niddah,
yes.
Absolutely. This discussion was the whole dimension of an עם הארץ, am
haaretz, right? Right. Right, you have to be careful about תרומה. terumah.
Right, it's like there's a presumption that we're talking with amongst—amongst חברים.
chaverim. But yeah, it's a good point, it could say if he's
marrying a woman who's an
עם הארץ, am haaretz, then—and—well, if he himself was an עם הארץ,
am haaretz, I don't know if he's going to care. But I
mean we have to—well, you mean like בית דין Beis Din would
oversee, maybe. But certainly if he's—I mean, the bigger concern that we
normally address is can a חבר chaver give תרומה terumah to an
עם הארץ? am haaretz? So, that would be obviously a very relevant—then
he might not be even be able to give half and half.
You're right, it's a very good point, yes.
The assumption in מסכת דמאי Masechet Demai is that people are generally
careful of תרומה. terumah.
They're
careful with separating תרומה, terumah, but not necessarily—but עמי הארץ, amei haaretz,
the assumption is that they're always טמא tamei and they're not careful
about making things טמא. tamei. So that's—and that which is—and
therefore they would wind up eating תרומה טמאה, terumah tmeiah, right? So
they're careful to separate תרומה, terumah, but that's correct. Okay, so גמרא
Gemara says, so number one is, if we're going to give her
all תרומה, terumah, which is a pretty serious challenge, it has to
be that she's already a בת כהן. bas kohen. ואמר אביי, Ve-amar
Abaye, מחלוקת בארוסה. machlokes be-arusa.
All of this is—and here Michael, it answers your question—all of this
is while she is still only an ארוסה, arusa, but the twelve
months have arrived. And therefore we're giving the בעל baal a little
bit more latitude and so on. אבל בנשואה, Aval be-nisuah, if there's
already נשואין nisuin and they're already living together, דברי הכל מחצה חולין
מחצה תרומה. divrei hakol mechtza chulin mechtza terumah.
Then everybody says it's half and half, right? Because even though
then—right, because—let me just check for a minute.
I don't get that at all. She's living in his house.
Okay, so רש"י Rashi says the explanation is, so I would have
said like Michael, that's why I was double-checking רש"י. Rashi. I would
have said like Michael, the explanation is that we're going easy on
him because he's having to pay her bills even before—even before they're
married. But רש"י Rashi says, and this fits into the next thing
in the גמרא, Gemara, that part of the reason also is keeping
within this context of the burden of giving her all תרומה terumah
and will she be able to face up to that challenge when
she's a נדה niddah and so on. is that if she's living
in her father's house, then the father can take care of selling
it for her. There's an assumption that the woman is not going
to be easy in a society in which women were basically at
home, for the woman to have to on her own go ahead
and try to convert this תרומה terumah into חולין. chullin. But if
she's living in her father's house, the father can take care. Once
she's נשואה, nesu'ah, now the question is when she's נשואה, nesu'ah, why
is he sending her the food? If she's נשואה, nesu'ah, they should
be eating at the same table. But there are cases where some
marriages are different where he actually maybe he's I don't know, on
a business trip or something like that, and she's living, they're נשואין,
nesu'in, they are married but she's living alone from him, and he
actually is making sure that she's getting her food that she's getting
the food that she needs. In that case, she doesn't have a
father, the husband is off on some business trip, she doesn't have
a father to be selling the תרומה terumah for her, so in
that case we have to provide her חצי חולין חצי תרומה. chatzi
chullin chatzi terumah. So the basic point is, the possibility that you
give her all תרומה terumah is very challenging. It's challenging when she's
a נידה niddah to know to be careful about that and to
have the right and if it's especially if it's going to be
difficult to convert that, are you going to be able to sort
of have the proper care and ensure that you do convert it?
And it's a challenge to go to the market and to convert
it. So therefore the possibility that it's all תרומה terumah is only
going to be both if she's a בת כהן bat kohen and
knows the level of care that's needed, and that she is in
her father's house and the father can help her
get sort of converted into חולין. chullin.
Wait, so in a married couple's house, Mr. and Mrs.
Cohen, and she was a בת, bat, no, doesn't matter, so Mr.
and Mrs. Cohen, they have two refrigerators, a חולין chullin refrigerator and
a תרומה terumah refrigerator.
Basically, yep. And he doesn't eat from the חולין chullin refrigerator.
He can eat from the חולין chullin fridge. She doesn't eat from
the תרומה terumah one when she's a
נידה. niddah. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: תניא נמי
הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly: רבי טרפון אומר נותנין לה
הכל תרומה, Rabbi Tarfon omer notnin lah hakol terumah, Rabbi Tarfon says
we give her all תרומה. terumah. רבי עקיבא אומר מחצה חולין ומחצה
תרומה, Rabbi Akiva omer mechtza chullin u-mechtza terumah, Rabbi Akiva says half
and half. במה דברים אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim, when is this true?
בבת כהן לכהן. Be-bat kohen le-kohen. אבל בת ישראל לכהן, Aval bat
Yisrael le-kohen, when does Rabbi Tarfon say all תרומה? terumah? If it's
only she's coming from a כהן kohen house. But if she's coming
from ישראל Yisrael house, דברי הכל מחצה חולין ומחצה תרומה, divrei hakol
mechtza chullin u-mechtza terumah, he would not force on her all תרומה,
terumah, that wouldn't be reasonable because she'd be a נידה niddah and
she's not used to it. במה דברים אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim, when
is it true that Rabbi Tarfon says all תרומה? terumah? בארוסה, Be-arusa,
when she's still an ארוסה arusa but the twelve months have arrived
and therefore if you give her all תרומה terumah at least the
father will take care of selling it. אבל בנשואה, Aval be-nesu'ah,
once she's a נשואה nesu'ah and there's nobody around to help her
with it, in that case, even if she, in that case, דברי
הכל מחצה חולין ומחצה תרומה. divrei hakol mechtza chullin u-mechtza terumah. Now
what's pretty interesting here is you had these as statements of אביי
Abaye and then you have תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, word
for word what אביי Abaye said. Who needed אביי Abaye to say
this? Just quote the
ברייתא. baraita. And if אביי Abaye didn't know the ברייתא baraita it's
still could be interesting that it's word for word what the ברייתא
baraita said. So there actually is an interesting phenomenon that scholars have
noted, that there are ברייתות baraitot that are not found in the
ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, that are only found in the בבלי, Bavli, and often
those ברייתות baraitot are word for word the same statements of an
אמורא. Amora. So you will actually have an אמורא Amora who says,
אמר אביי, amar Abaye, A-B-C-D, תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, A-B-C-D,
word for word what the אמורא Amora said. So why did we
need you? Just quote the ברייתא. baraita. And interestingly, often those ברייתות
baraitot have no parallel anywhere else in ש״ס. Shas. So the question
becomes, is it possible that an אמורא Amora statement got somehow remembered
as a ברייתא, baraita, or the reverse, that something was being
אביי Abaye was quoting a ברייתא, baraita, but then it got remembered
as אביי Abaye's statement alone? But there is some interesting that it's
word for word what אביי Abaye said and often those types of
ברייתות baraitot are not found anywhere else. All right, so anyway that's
what we have, that רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon is saying that this
is all תרומה, terumah, but only if we can feel confident that
she'll be able to know the need to convert it to חולין
chullin and convert it to חולין chullin once she was coming from
a כהן kohen house and is still living with her father. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, רבי יהודה בן בתירה, Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira, now we have
another opinion, רבי יהודה בן בתירה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer,
נותנין לה שתי ידות של תרומה ואחת של חולין, notnin lah shtei
yadot shel terumah ve-achat shel chullin,
two-thirds תרומה, terumah, one-third חולין, chullin, which more closely matches the period
in which she'll be a נידה. niddah. Being, not giving her as
much breathing room there, making it more demanding but paralleling the period
when she'll be a נידה niddah and not be a נידה. niddah.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, נותנין לה הכל תרומה, notnin lah
hakol terumah,
you give her all תרומה, terumah, so it sounds like רבי טרפון,
Rabbi Tarfon, but והיא מוכרת ולוקחת בדמי חולין, ve-hi mocheret ve-lokachat bi-dmei
chullin,
she'll buy חולין. chullin. So what's he saying
different than רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon other than telling us what's obvious,
that she has to sell it? So רש״י Rashi says what he's
saying different than רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon is, is that he gives
her so much תרומה terumah that she can buy the necessary amount
of חולין, chullin, meaning if תרומה terumah goes for, if חולין chullin
goes for ten dollars a bag... bag of whatever flour and תרומה
Truma goes for eight dollars a bag of flour, so then he
has to and he has to give her I don't know ten
bags and normally he would give her ten bags of flour for
the week, so he's got to give her now I got to
do the math but he's got to give her like 12 bags
of תרומה Truma flour so she can convert it into 10 bags
of חולין Chulin flour. Okay which obviously makes sense. How can he
give the same amount that she can't eat and it goes for
less and she has to convert it she's gonna have to eat
less food during that week. So he says okay so you give
her more תרומה. Truma. You give her... she still has to do
the effort of selling it but you give her the dollar value
that's equivalent to the amount of חולין Chulin that she needs to
be eating during that time. Okay, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel אומר, omer, כל מקום שהוזכרה תרומה kol makom she'huzkera truma
whenever we say that he gives her תרומה, truma, נותן לה כפליים
בחולין. noten lah kiflayim bachulin.
You actually give her double which is much more. תרומה Truma wasn't
50% of you know didn't go for half of חולין, chulin, it
maybe went for two-thirds of חולין, chulin, but doesn't matter, you give
her double the amount of תרומה truma than you would normally give
her חולין. chulin. Okay מאי בינייהו, mai beinayhu, what's the difference, meaning
why are they having different opinions? איכא בינייהו טירחא ika beinayhu tircha
because if I have to convert, you know, if it's going at
80 cents to the dollar then I have to actually go and
handle and you know wait till I get my asking price and
it takes time. If I can go ahead and it's going 80
cents to the dollar and I say go put it up on
eBay in a special sale and whatever and I'm offering it at
50 cents to the dollar I'll get it sold in two seconds.
So therefore if you want to give her תרומה truma you have
to give it to her in a way that she can very
easily convert it into an the amount of חולין chulin that she's
entitled.
He's giving her some compensation for the תרומה truma bit, what
we're saying, yeah, right,
and what's also actually interesting is these last two opinions that says
he has to give her more תרומה, truma, is that even during
the first two weeks? Meaning it sounds like, right, if I'm going
to give her תרומה truma the entire period even though she might
only be a נידה niddah for one week out of the month,
I'm going to have to according to this last opinion give her
double תרומה truma for the whole month. Okay, so effectively I have
to make it possible for her to eat חולין chulin the whole
month, okay, but I'm allowed to give her תרומה truma if it
can be then converted into the right amount of חולין chulin for
the whole month.
So yeah, we don't know that. In other words, they might have
said no no no we mean for those weeks.
No but it's not clear which weeks. Meaning you have all way
at the beginning you had an opinion half and half, then you
said all, then you said two-thirds. So they're not... they're not saying
תרומה truma for this amount of period. Right, says a period all,
half, two-thirds and they're just saying whenever you give her תרומה truma
you gotta give her double. Sounds like even for the whole month,
that's what it sounds like to me. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay, so that's the issue about what he
can feed her with but her then making it possible for it
to be reasonable for her to use that.
היבם אינו מאכיל בתרומה. Hayavam eino ma'achil b'truma.
If the כהן kohen who she's married to, well two scenarios, one
is he's in... it's only אירוסין eirusin and he dies and then
she falls before the brother-in-law or even נישואין nisuin and he dies
and she falls before the brother-in-law, can she eat תרומה truma now?
It's like a period of קידושין kiddushin before נישואין, nisuin, right, because
now there's this זיקה. zika. Everybody remembers יבמות, Yevamos, but they haven't
started living together. So maybe... and maybe it's even better than the
12 months, he's a מצוה mitzvah to do יבום. yibum. Okay, nevertheless
the משנה mishna says that during this period of יבום yibum and
זיקה zika she can't eat תרומה. truma. She has to wait until
they actually do the יבום yibum itself.
זיקה Zika has the legal force of being analogous to a kind
of
קידושין kiddushin or...?
It's a quasi-קידושין, kiddushin,
right. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the
reason? קניין כספו, kinyan kaspo, אמר רחמנא, amar rachmana, the only way
he was... she was able to eat was because actually it was
full קידושין, kiddushin, that was... I mean that's how we allowed it
before נישואין nisuin after the 12 months. Okay, והאי קניין דאחיו הוא.
v'hai kinyan d'achiv hu. This isn't his קניין כספו, kinyan kaspo, it's
his brother's. And we might actually say that even though there is
some זיקה, zika, it's not the full force of the זיקה zika
of קידושין kiddushin and therefore she's not entitled to eat before the
act of יבום yibum even once the 12 months have arrived. Okay,
עשתה שישה חודשים בפני הבעל. Ashtah shisha chodashim bifnei habaal. Now if
it was six months with the... after the קידושין kiddushin of the
כהן kohen after they were getting ready to get... yes.
קניין כספו, kinyan kaspo, it seems to be redundant because the פסוק
pasuk is וכל כהן כי
יקנה נפש
קניין כספו.
v'chol kohen ki yikneh nefesh
kinyan kaspo.
But the... והאשה נקנית, v'ha'isha nikneis, it does not
have to be with כסף. kesef.
Right, so... so I mean תוספות Tosafos already or רש"י, Rashi, I
forget, points out that whether it would be even if it would
be like קידושי ביאה, kiddushei biah, obviously it would still... she could
still eat תרומה. truma. But I think the reason that the גמרא
Gemara is underscoring is קניין כספו kinyan kaspo is because the גמרא
Gemara doesn't just want to simply sort of bundle, you know, the...
the woman with the slave. Okay, if you acquire somebody, slave or
a woman. So it wants to somehow say that the extra language
of קניין כספו kinyan kaspo is coming to... to address a different
type of a קניין, kinyan, the קניין kinyan of קידושין. kiddushin. So
I think it's doing so as not to just make it simply
in the same category as the slave. But it...
so that's why I think it's, you know, you know. It’s not
just saying oh קידושין kiddushin is קנין, kinyan, because to just say
without an extra language in the פסוק, pasuk, it wouldn't differentiate it.
But you are correct that regardless of whether קידושין kiddushin כסף kesef
or קידושין kiddushin ביאה biah or whatever, that would be this הלכה
halacha would obtain. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אשה ששה חודשים בפני הבעל. isha shisha chodashim bifnei habaal.
So six months she was since the time since they were getting
ready to get married, right, and then after 12 months she would
eat, and then he dies, and then six months with the יבם,
yavam, it doesn't count. And then it says even if it's 11
months and 29 days, one month away from the time she'd begin
to eat, the extra what's the fact that then he dies and
then it's the יבם, yavam, she doesn't get to eat. So the
גמרא Gemara says השתא בפני הבעל אמרת לא בפני היבם מיבעיא. hashta
bifnei habaal amarta lo bifnei hayavam mibaya. So if the משנה Mishnah
says 11 months and 29 days doesn't work with the husband and
one day from the בעל, baal, why do you have to do
the next case? Which it said that if it was all in
front of the יבם yavam and one day, you know,
11 months in front of יבם, yavam, it doesn't work. Of course
the יבם, yavam,
you know, that's obvious. זו וזו ואין צריך לומר זו קתני. zu
vezu veein tzarich lomar zu katani. Fine, this and it goes without
saying that.
But ששה חודשים shisha chodashim came first though. What? The ששה חודשים
shisha chodashim then 11 months.
It says ואפילו כולם
בפני הבעל חסר יום אחד בפני היבם או כולם בפני
היבם חסר יום אחד בפני הבעל. veafilu kulam
bifnei habaal chasar yom echad bifnei hayavam o kulam bifnei
hayavam chasar yom echad bifnei habaal.
So why do you need to tell me כולם בפני היבם? kulam
bifnei hayavam? If you told me כולם בפני הבעל kulam bifnei habaal
it doesn't work, obviously if כולם בפני היבם. kulam bifnei hayavam.
I was thinking of the ששה חודשים shisha chodashim part. Right. Okay,
yeah, yeah. Okay, now זו משנה ראשונה.
zu mishna rishona. This was the first teaching, that after 12 months
she begins to eat תרומה, trumah, but then they said that she
doesn't begin to eat תרומה trumah until the actual חופה. chuppah. Okay,
so we're back to the תרומה. trumah. He does have to pay
the food bills, but she doesn't eat תרומה trumah until the actual
חופה. chuppah. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי טעמא? mai taama? Why
did they stop say we don't want her eating תרומה trumah even
after the 12 months? אמר עולא ואיתימא רב שמואל בר יהודה משום
סימפון. amar Ula veeitema Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda mishum simpon.
The same reason we said before that even though it's after 12
months, we're still afraid, we're afraid that after they're intimate, there'll be
something that'll lead to ביטול קידושין. bitul kiddushin. So the גמרא Gemara
says okay, one minute. How does that get us, how is that
different from what we've been saying until now?
בשלמא לעולא כמעיקרא שמא ימזגו לה כוס של תרומה ואסיביה. bishlama leula
kemeikara shema yimzgu la kos shel trumah vaseiveia. Initially we said we
thought the only concern was she would share with her family and
therefore we said after 12 months she won't be living with her
family, we're not concerned, so we allowed her to have תרומה trumah
after 12 months. ולבסוף משום סימפון. ulevasof mishum simpon. And then we
said, you know what, we shouldn't allow even after 12 months because
in addition to the problem of sharing with her family, maybe there'll
be some problem and it'll lead to ביטול קידושין. bitul kiddushin. So
that was the new, the new sort of, you know, approach that
told us wait until the actual חופה. chuppah. That we get, we
get the stage of development. Okay, אלא לרב שמואל בר יהודה, ela
leRav Shmuel bar Yehuda, but according to רב שמואל בר יהודה Rav
Shmuel bar Yehuda what he said earlier, the beginning of today's דף,
daf, כמעיקרא משום סימפון. kemeikara mishum simpon. At the very beginning we
said don't do it right away because there might be a ביטול
מקח, bitul mekach, and we figured that after 12 months maybe he'd
be confident enough. So then what led us from saying 12 months
isn't enough, you need to wait till the חופה? chuppah? It's all
about a concern of ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. So the גמרא Gemara
says כמעיקרא משום סימפון ולבסוף משום סימפון. kemeikara mishum simpon ulevasof mishum
simpon. Initially we said we were concerned that there would be some
flaw, some problem, and at the end we were concerned there would
be some problem. So why in the beginning did we think 12
months was okay and in the end we decided we had to
wait till the חופה? chuppah? So the גמרא Gemara says מאי בינייהו?
mai beinaihu? What led from one to the next? איכא בינייהו בדיקת
חוץ. ika beinaihu bdikat chutz. Checking around without, you know, by asking
other people. Okay, doing a background check might be a good might
be a good phrase
for בדיקת חוץ. bdikat chutz. מר סבר בדיקת חוץ שמה בדיקה. mar
savar bdikat chutz shma bdika. We figured what we figured was after
12 months he would have the opportunity to do a background check
and to talk to relatives. Okay, so therefore we thought that would
be enough and we weren't afraid after 12 months something would go
wrong. ומר סבר בדיקת חוץ לא שמה בדיקה. umar savar bdikat chutz
lo shma bdika. The other said, you know what, background checks is
one thing, once you start living with a person it's a different
thing, and therefore we said 12 months isn't going to be enough,
we're going to have to wait until they actually begin to live
together before we can stop being concerned that this might happen. Okay,
so that is the issue about when they should be getting married
and the חיוב chiyuv of מזונות. mezonot. And what I have to
say is we're framing what we're getting into, the section we're getting
into now in the גמרא Gemara is, you know, we sort of
talked about the basic obligations of what's written in the כתובה ketubah
and מעשה ידיה maaseh yadeha and the core amounts and, you know,
and his obligation and now we are turning into this, this issue
about these which I would say is the core of כתובות Ketubot
which is the reciprocal obligations during marriage. So he has to feed
her and that can sometimes start already before the קידושין kiddushin נישואין
nissuin when the נישואין nissuin should have taken place. And then in
exchange he's entitled to her מעשה ידיה maaseh yadeha her labor. And
now these are the next types of discussions we're going to be
happening, having around this issue about his obligations to her and her
obligations or his, you know, right he has to her earnings and
so on from, you know, to him.
So how much time can go by
for a סימפון simpon claim to stay...
Yeah, that's a good question, and it comes up.
Ten years go by, probably, he wants to get divorced, he says,
"Listen," or she wants to get divorced, right? And so he says,
"You know what, I've been living with this thing for ten years."
Right, so often we would say that there could be an issue
of like סבר וקיבל, savar vekibel, which is basically if you, you
know, if you knew about it and you didn't raise it until
now, then it's basically saying that you don't see this as something
that's so fundamental that leads to a
ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. You know, so often it has to be
pretty soon after it was discovered, but not soon after after you've
lived with them. Right, again, I mean I'm sorry to keep on
using this case, but it's a context that really, you know, is
like a one that happens contemporary is, you know, 10 years into
the marriage, find out that the husband's gay and he knew about
it all along and he was hiding it or something like that,
right? So it doesn't matter that it happened 10 years, what matters
is that now you found out and now it's just... Right, exactly.
All right, the other cases, you know, I mean it's so often
it's funny, I mean it could be, the גמרא Gemara always talks
about the problem with the woman, but the cases I always hear
the problems with the guy. Like you know, thought he was this
lawyer in this law firm or whatever, turns out he was telling
her a whole story, right? He's unemployed, he's, you know, he's a
pathological liar, these types of things. But it could be you find
out six months into the marriage. Okay. So those things happen. All
right. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: המקדיש מעשה ידי אשתו,
Hamakdish ma'aseh yedei ishto,
by the way, those are really like מסכת קידושין Masechet Kiddushin types
of questions, but they are interesting ones. We'll get to just aware
that we're not going to see much more of that in כתובות,
Ketubot, we'll see it more in קידושין. Kiddushin. המקדיש מעשה ידי אשתו.
Hamakdish ma'aseh yedei ishto. A man basically says, "I sanctify all of
the labor that my wife does and that should be קדוש." kadosh.
So there is a, you know, question here about like מקדיש דבר
שלא בא לעולם makdish davar shelo ba l'olam possibly, but we're going
to bracket that concern. The real concern is, right, because the things
don't exist yet, the real concern is who owns them? If he's
considered enough of an owner of his wife's labor, I mean he's
entitled to his wife's labor, that he could sanctify it. So the
משנה Mishnah says, הרי זו עושה ואוכלת. harei zo osah v'ochelet. She
goes ahead, she does her labor, she can go ahead and, you
know, eat from, either it means eat from the labor itself, that
what she produced is not sanctified, or, and he goes, we'll see
in the גמרא, Gemara, he continues to feed her because it's normally
the exchange is he feeds her for her מעשה ידיים. ma'aseh yadayim.
So even if he has to go ahead and continue to feed
her and but what she does is still not sanctified. Okay.
So he can't benefit from it?
No, it's not sanctified. It didn't work.
It's another way of saying it didn't work.
לא אמר כלום Lo amar klum is essentially what it
says.
Okay. So הרי זו עושה ואוכלת, harei zo osah v'ochelet, she can
do whatever and he can also use it?
Yeah, or she can eat from it, he can eat from it,
but אוכלת ochelet also might mean the context that he still has
to pay for her labor, you know, he has to feed her
and you would think that he's entitled to her labor, but nevertheless
it's not sanctified. Okay. We'll see why in the גמרא. Gemara.
She's not allowed to be מקדיש makdish her מעשה? ma'aseh?
All right, yeah, that's clear. Well whatever, we'll see why in the
גמרא. Gemara. Now the other thing you have to know as we're
going to see a משנה Mishnah that says that even it's one
thing to say she's he's entitled to her labor if she goes
ahead and decides to go out and get a job. But let's
say she doesn't want to go out and get a job. She
just wants to sit home all day, there are no kids, she
wants to sit home and watch TV, right? What is when he's
entitled to her מעשה ידיים, ma'aseh yadayim, the משנה Mishnah later is
actually going to spell out that she has a responsibility to produce
a certain amount, like you know, maybe to take up a work
as a seamstress or something like that, to produce a certain amount
even if there's no, even if, you know, she's not interested and
he can still say you got to you got to start, you
know, contributing to the household. All right, so and then the משנה
Mishnah defines how much that minimum amount is. So המותר, hamotar, מותר
motar is the work she does beyond the minimum amount, okay? She
goes ahead, she doesn't want to be a seamstress, she goes ahead
and she does online investing in the stock market and she makes
a million dollars, okay? So while she's כל כבודה בת מלך פנימה
kol kvudah bat melech pnimah and staying home, okay? So what about
that extra amount? So he's also entitled to the extra amount as
well, the same way he's entitled to the מעשה ידיים. ma'aseh yadayim.
But what you have to know is to anticipate what the גמרא
Gemara is going to say is the normal type of equivalency is
because he pays the food bill, he's entitled to the minimum amount
that she does that we're going to define, and because he gives
her a little extra for like for שבת Shabbos and for the
weekend, which it's going to tell you he gives her a מעה
סלע, ma'ah sela, he gives her an extra, you know, twenty bucks
as a little like discretionary spending. Pin money, thank you. So therefore
he's entitled to the מותר. motar. He's entitled to anything she produces
beyond that minimum amount. Okay. So what we said the basic stuff
which you would think he's more entitled to he can't sanctify. המותר,
hamotar, the additional amount, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir הקדש, hekdesh, that is
sanctified. רבי יוחנן הסנדלר Rabbi Yochanan HaSandlar חולין, chullin, that's not. So
it's very bizarre why would the extra amount be more his to
sanctify than the core amount? So we're going to see this in
the גמרא.
Gemara. I want to understand. So we're saying that she's expected, make
sure this... Meaning like, but keeping house and like cooking the food
is, no, no, no. Right, that's not considered מעשה ידיה? Ma'aseh Yadeha?
No, it is. I think so. The משנה Mishnah says on, I
mean, let's not get into this right now.
I mean, but the משנה Mishnah is going to say later she
doesn't necessarily have to have a job, meaning, but meaning working in
the home is enough too.
In other words, מעשה ידיה Ma'aseh Yadeha really is מעשה ידיה. Ma'aseh
Yadeha. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I think this מסכת Masechet was written in
the early 1950s. Okay, I mean, let's hold off on that, okay?
I don't remember exactly. Okay, let's hold off on that.
It's coming up. It's coming up.
Okay, אמר רב הונא אמר
רב.
Amar Rav
Huna Amar Rav.
So רב הונא Rav Huna says in
the name of
רב, Rav, יכולה אשה לומר לבעלה. Yechola isha lomar le'ba'ala. Now this
is a really important line we're about to see.
יכולה, Yechola, but which
talks about the whole way in which it's framed, יכולה אשה לומר
לבעלה, Yechola isha lomar le'ba'ala, a woman could say
to her husband, איני ניזונת ואיני עושה, Eini nizonet ve'eini osa, that
I will not, you don't have to pay my food bill, I'm
not
going to do work for the house. Or another way to say
it is, or a separate way of saying it is, any work
I do, earnings I do, I'll keep. Okay, so this is a
really important question. Who is the primary person in charge, you know,
for whom the כתובה Kesuvah is for the benefit of? Is it
fundamentally to protect her or is it fundamentally for his right? And
what this is saying is it's fundamentally to protect her, which in
her interest that she be get that he pay the food bill,
and in exchange, he's entitled to earnings. But fundamentally, it's for her
benefit, benefiting her. So therefore, if she feels it's not in her
interest, she can basically, she can, right, she can reverse, she can
annul that, or she can like say, I don't, you know what,
keep your food bill, I'll keep my earnings. Okay, and by the
way, this is important because in ישראל, Yisrael, the כתובה Kesuvah is
used actually as a legal document. If in a case of divorce,
they go to a בית דין Beis Din as opposed to בית
משפט. Beis Mishpat. And I think now because they passed a law
in the כנסת, Knesset, what I'm about to say isn't as necessary,
but there was a period where what they actually did is they're
קולך, Kolech, you know, people sort of like these, you know, groups
that were interested in protecting women's interests, basically had a rider to
the כתובה Kesuvah that the woman actually said איני ניזונת ואיני עושה
Eini nizonet ve'eini osa because you know, a woman could often be
a higher earner than the husband. Well, not in the כתובה, Kesuvah,
as a separate document, but she basically said, I'm not, you know,
you don't pay my food bill, I'm going to keep my own
earnings. And then you had one of two options: either separate bank
accounts and everybody's entitled to their own earnings, or if you wanted
to do the standard which was like you know, sort of what's
it called, not communal property, what's it called, shared property, community property,
I guess. Anyway, so then after, now everybody's entitled to their own
earnings and has no financial obligations to the other person. Now you
say, now we're agreeing to share our earnings and to have reciprocal
and to have parallel obligations to one another. Okay, so that's you
know, so you could construct that reality and it's in her power
to do that because the whole כתובה Kesuvah is framed to protect
her interest. That's what רב הונא Rav Huna is saying now in
the name of רב. Rav. She is exercising her legal right. She
has a legal right, yes. So six months go by, she changes
her mind, she can simply reverse it, take it back, and the
כתובה Kesuvah kicks in again. Right, that is an excellent point and
yes. Some things if you want to change, you would have to
change before the כתובה Kesuvah began altogether. Other things such as this,
the sense is that that's ongoing. If at any time she wants
to actually say, she gets fired from her job and she actually
says, actually now let's go back, you pay my food bill and
I'll do whatever work I have to do at home, then she's
entitled. It's done for her interest. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says קסבר, Kasavar, he holds כי תקינו רבנן מזוני, Ki takinu rabanan
mezoni, כי תקינו רבנן, Ki takinu rabanan, when the rabbis established the
כתובה, Kesuvah, מזוני עיקר, Mezoni ikar, the real, the real תקנה Takana
was to make sure that she got her food, you know, מזוני,
Mezoni, that her food bill was paid. ומעשה ידיה משום איבה, U'ma'aseh
yadeha mishum eiva, and then once he was paying the food bill,
he was entitled to the earnings. But it starts with her being
entitled to have the food bill paid. וכי אמרה איני ניזונת ואיני
עושה, Ve'chi amra eini nizonet ve'eini osa, and when she wants to
say, you know what, I don't want you to pay for my
food then I want to keep my earnings, הרשות בידה, Ha'reshut beyada,
she has the right to do this. Okay, מיתיבי. Meisivei. It really
means that she has no obligation, she has no obligation to the
husband in this regard, but it's just not viable. Yeah, but okay,
but מזוני עיקר. Mezoni ikar. Well, no, but that's more about what
motivated the תקנה. Takana. Once we made the תקנה, Takana, she does
have an obligation. But that obligation is only if she is getting
the, if she's having the food bill paid, if she's being, if
he's paying the מזונות. Mezonos. Okay, מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you on
this: תקנו מזונות תחת מעשה ידיה. Tiknu mezonot tachat ma'aseh yadeha. We
have a ברייתא Braita that says that we gave her מזונות Mezonot
in exchange for her מעשה ידיה. Ma'aseh yadeha. It sounds like the
foundation was he's entitled to her earnings and מזונות Mezonot was what
was done to. Say it's the reverse. אימא *Eima* say it's the
reverse. תקנו מעשה ידיה תחת מזונות *tiknu ma'aseh yadeha tachat mezonot*. Okay,
reversing. It means that they gave her his earnings since they had
fundamentally given her the right of מזונות *mezonot*. Okay. לימא מסייע ליה
*leima mesayei lei*. Now let's try to support this idea from our
משנה Mishnah. *mishnah*. המקדיש מעשה ידי אשתו *hamakdish ma'aseh yedei ishto*, a
man sanctifies his wife's earnings, הרי היא עושה ואוכלת *harei hi osa
v'ochelet*. So she gets so they're not sanctified. מאי לאו במזונות *mai
lav bimzonot*. We must be talking about a case where he is
prepared to pay the food bill, and even though he's prepared to
pay the food bill, he can't sanctify it. Why can't he sanctify
it? So תוספות *Tosafot* says he can't sanctify it because he wants
to pay the food bill, but she is saying, no, I don't
accept the food, I'm keeping my מעשה ידיים *ma'aseh yadayim*, and therefore
it's not sanctified. I would go even further, and I would say
that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is indicating that even if she didn't
say no, even if she's agreeing to be fed and have the
earnings go to him, since at any moment she's entitled to say
I'm going to keep my earnings, who's the real owner of those
of that labor? She's the owner, she's the one who has the
power, right? She's the one in control. Is that clear? So even
if he is actually paying the food bill and getting her earnings,
since at any moment she can say stop, I'm keeping it, then
who's the owner to sanctify the earnings? She's the owner, not him.
Once the earnings actually transfer to him, let him sanctify it, but
before those earnings have transferred, she's the בעל הבית ba'al habayit, *ba'al
habayit*. It's her. She's totally in control about whether she's going to
keep on giving it to him or whether she's going to keep
it to herself. As long as she has the power to say
no, exactly, he's not the owner and has therefore no legal ability
to sanctify them. Until once she actually gives him the earnings, sanctify
all the way, but before that she's the owner. Okay, so that
seems to prove this idea. מאי לאו במזונות *mai lav bimzonot*. לאו
בשאינה ניזונת *lav beshe'eina nizonet*. No, it's a case he's not paying
the food bills. And since he so maybe we would say she
does not have a right to say no, it's his power, okay,
to say that I can he can say keep your earnings, I
won't feed you, but she can't. So therefore why is so he
is totally in control, so why can't he sanctify it? Because it's
a case where he is saying I'm not going to feed you.
And since he's saying I'm not going to feed you, she's entitled
to keep the earnings. So that's the case of the משנה Mishnah.
*mishnah*. It doesn't sound like it. It doesn't sound like the משנה
Mishnah *mishnah* is such a special case. And anyway the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is going to say is he entitled to do that? Like
even if she's not entitled to say no, is he entitled to
say no? Is he entitled to say I refuse to pay your
food bills? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute. אי בשאינה
ניזונת *ei beshe'eina nizonet*, if he's not paying the food bills, מאי
למימרא *mai l'memra*, then what's the חידוש *chiddush*? Then of course she
keeps her own earnings. אפילו למאן דאמר יכול הרב לומר לעבד עשה
עמי ואיני זנך *afilu leman de'amar yakol harav lomar l'eved aseh imi
v'eini zanach*. There's an opinion that a master can say to the
slave, a non-Jewish slave, that you have to work for me and
I refuse to feed you, that he could be entitled to the
work of the slave even without feeding the slave. Even according to
that position, הני מילי בעבד כנעני *hani mili be'eved Kna'ani*, that's by
a non-Jewish slave. לא כתיב עמך *lo ketiv imach*. It doesn't say
he shall be with you, so you don't have that fundamental the
same level of responsibility towards him. אבל עבד עברי *aval eved Ivri*,
a Jewish slave, דכתיב עמך *dechetiv imach*, he should be with you,
לא *lo*, you wouldn't be entitled to the work of a Jewish
slave without feeding him, וכל שכן אשתו *v'chol sheken ishto*, and certainly
one's wife. So if רב *Rav*'s statement is not correct, if the
husband has all the power, then he should be the one that
owns the earnings fundamentally and be entitled to sanctify. And if the
only way to say no is that he's refusing to feed his
wife, and since he's refusing to feed his wife, he's not entitled
to the earnings, so the גמרא *Gemara* says well that's obvious. Nobody
would ever have a question that if he refused to feed his
wife, he wouldn't be entitled to the earnings. Of course not. So
what's the חידוש *chiddush* of the משנה *mishnah*? So the גמרא *Gemara*
says, here's the חידוש *chiddush*. סיפא איצטריכא ליה *seifa itztricha lei*. You
need the משנה *mishnah* for the end, to tell you the issue
about the additional amount. מותר motar *motar* רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir אומר
הקדש *Rabbi Meir omer hekdesh* רבי יוחנן הסנדלר אומר חולין *Rabbi Yochanan
Hasandlar omer chullin*. Okay, so we're going to have to see why
they argue about the additional amount, but anyway, but that's why it's
teaching it to you. Yes, obviously the core amount he's not entitled
to because he's not feeding her. So we have two explanations now
of the משנה *mishnah*. One is he's not entitled to the earnings
because he's not feeding her. And the other is even though he
is entitled to the earnings, he's not the בעל הבית *ba'al habayit*,
she's the בעל הבית *ba'al habayit*, she's the one that can say
no. And therefore he is not in a position to sanctify them.
Okay, let's now get finished up to the two dots. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says like this. ופליגא דריש לקיש *ufliga deResh Lakish*. This
approach of רב הונא אמר רב Rav Huna Amar Rav. *Rav Huna
amar Rav* argues on ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Resh Lakish*. דאמר ריש
לקיש *de'amar Resh Lakish*, לא תימה טעמיה דרבי מאיר משום דקסבר אדם
מקדיש דבר שלא בא לעולם Davar she-lo ba la-olam. *lo teima ta'amei
deRabbi Meir mishum dekasavar adam makdish davar shelo ba l'olam*. Why does
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* say that you can sanctify the
additional amount? Okay, we're not yet discussing why the additional is different
than the core. Why does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say that you
can't sanctify—I'm sorry, that you can sanctify the additional amount? Okay, we're
not yet discussing why the additional is different than the core. But
why does he basically say you can sanctify? Don't say because he
holds you can sanctify something that has not yet existed, right? דבר
שלא בא לעולם. davar she-lo ba la-olam, Can you sanctify it, can
you own it, can you buy it, can you sell it? Don't
say that's the logic. Besides who owns it, that fundamentally even though
it's לא בא לעולם lo ba la-olam you can sanctify. אלא טעמא
דרבי מאיר מתוך שיכול לכופה למעשה ידיה, Ella ta'ama de-Rabbi Meir mi-tokh
she-yakhol l'kofah l'ma'aseh yadeha, since he can force her to do the
work, נעשה כאומר לה, na'aseh ke-omer lah, it's like he said when
he said I'm sanctifying what you produce, he didn't really mean I'm
sanctifying what you produce. What he really meant to say is יקדשו
ידיך לעושיהם. yikdeshu yadekh l'oseihem. I am sanctifying your hands to their
maker, to God. Which basically is what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
saying is the following: basically, this is where it argues on רב
הונא אמר רב. It's an idea ריש לקיש is assuming that the
husband can—the husband's in control, the husband has power. The wife—he could
say as long as I'm feeding you, you got to work for
me, you cannot say no. Since he has power and control, it's
like he owns his wife למעשה ידיים. l'ma'aseh yadayim. He actually like
has a monetary ownership in his wife for the right to her
labor. And he's the owner because she can't say no. And therefore
when he says I'm going to sanctify what she produces, it doesn't
mean I'm going to sanctify what comes later and I can sanctify
something that isn't in the world. I'm going to sanctify right now
that ownership that I have in my wife, the ownership—the monetary rights
I have in my wife to her labor. His wife to her
hand. To her—like not physical hands, but yes, to her labor. Exactly.
Exactly. Okay, so the גמרא has now presented us, before we get
to דבר שלא בא לעולם, davar she-lo ba la-olam, two very different
models. One is she is the בעלת הבית, ba'alat habayit, she can
say no, he doesn't have any rights and any ownership until she
actually gives it over. And the other is he's the בעל הבית,
she can't say no, and then it even becomes like rights in
her body, monetary rights. And therefore, what he could sanctify is not
just the produce later, but even those monetary rights right now. It's
just the מותר motar that he's saying this on. Yeah, why it's
just the מותר mosar? we'll worry about, but that's not our interest.
Right now our fundamental interest is in who has rights to her
labor. Okay, so let's just finish to the two dots. והא לא
אמר לה הכי, Ve-ha lo amar lah hakhi, but he didn't say
that. He didn't say I'm sanctifying my rights of in my wife's
hands. He said I'm sanctifying what she produces. No. כיון דשמעינן ליה
לרבי מאיר דאמר אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה, Keivan de-sham'inan lei le-Rabbi
Meir de-amar ein adam motzi devarav le-vattalah, since we know רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir in another context, which I don't want to get into,
which says that we don't—we assume people don't say you know things
that are of not no legal meaning. If somebody says something we're
going to interpret it so that it's in a legally meaningful way.
Even if it's not what you said, we're going to choose to
interpret it in a legally meaningful way. נעשה כאומר לה, Na'aseh ke-omer
lah, it's as if he said יקדשו ידיך לעושיהם, yikdeshu yadekh l'oseihem,
as if he's sanctifying his rights to his wife's in his wife's
hands and that's more effective than trying to sanctify what she produces
which is לא בא לעולם. lo ba la-olam. So the גמרא says
וסבר רבי מאיר אין אדם מקדיש דבר שלא בא לעולם? U-savar Rabbi
Meir ein adam makdish davar she-lo ba la-olam? I don't get it,
why are you driving yourself crazy to say that he's sanctifying the
rights in her hands? Since when does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say
you can't sanctify something that doesn't exist? רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
one of the ones that majorly says you can do things with
things that don't yet exist. והתניא, Ve-ha tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braitah, האומר לאשה הרי את מקודשת לי לאחר שאתגייר, Ha-omer le-ishah
harei at mekudeshet li le-akhar she-etgiayer, you are married to me after
I'll convert, או לאחר שתתגיירי o le-akhar she-titgayeri after you convert, או
לאחר שאשתחרר o le-akhar she-eshtakhrer after I become free, I'm a slave
right now, או לאחר שתשתחררי o le-akhar she-tishtakhreri or after you're freed,
או לאחר שימות בעליך, o le-akhar she-yamut ba'alakh, you're married to me
after your husband dies, או שתמות אחותיך, o she-tamut akhotekh, or your
sister who I'm married to dies and I'm not allowed to marry
you because you're my wife's sister, או לאחר שיחלוץ לך יבמיך, o
le-akhar she-yakhlotz lakh yavamikh, or after you get חליצה, chalitzah, רבי מאיר
אומר מקודשת. Rabbi Meir omer mekudeshet. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
it works. So even though that's similar to דבר שלא בא לעולם,
you see רבי מאיר is okay with it. So why did you
have to say you're sanctifying the hands? רבי מאיר is okay to
say you sanctify things that don't yet exist. Logically these are comparable.
גמרא says מההוא אין, Me-hahu in, yes, from there you can prove
that רבי מאיר could say you sanctify things that don't exist and
that could be the explanation of our משנה. מהא ליכא למשמע מינה,
Me-ha lekka le-mishma minnah, but it's just not obvious from our משנה.
From our משנה it could have been based on something else, it
could have been sanctifying the current rights he has, not the produce
that does not yet exist. So besides the issue of sanctifying something
that doesn't yet exist or sanctifying the ownership he has right now,
the core issue here which is so critical in terms of thinking
about what כתובות Ketubot is about—is it about the husband's rights or
is it about the wife's rights and protections—is who owns her earnings?
Either she owns her earnings and she's just willingly giving them to
him as long as she's accepting the food, but if she chooses
not to be—to accept the food, she fundamentally owns the earnings and
it's all her power, or does he fundamentally own the earnings and
as long as he's paying the food bill he's the one in
charge, she can't say no, and therefore so much to the point
that he might not just get the earnings when they're produced but
he has... So we have to answer why he's only, yeah, what's
the difference of מותר? Yeah. When did רב פפא? Rav Papa? That
we don't know. I think she, I'll see you tomorrow. Okay, thank
you.